software engineering radio episode 104
plug-in architecture this is software
engineering radio the podcast for
professional developers on the web at se
- radio dotnet se radio brings relevant
and detailed discussions and interviews
on soft engineering topics every 10 days
thanks to our audience and the partners
listed on our web site for supporting
the hot rod
[Music]
so welcome listeners to our new episode
on software engineering radio in this
episode we will talk about some
architecture stuff especially in this
episode we will talk about the
architecture style of building
applications out of plugins so the idea
of plugins and what is a plug-in will be
discussed in this episode and on the mic
is Martine and we have invited a guest
and the guest is Klaus Marquardt and I
would like to ask class Marquardt to
introduce himself so Klaus would you
introduce yourself yeah hello welcome
now thank you for the welcome my name is
Klaus Marquardt I work for Gregor
medical that is a company in lubeck
germany building life-supporting systems
like ventilation devices and unlike you
might expect I have no experience with
plugins using eclipse but instead I have
extensive experience using plugins in
for example medical applications I think
quite interesting so I have some
experiences using plugins with Eclipse
and you with some some some completely
different domain so as I think we will
have fun okay so I think let's let's
dive right into the topic right ok ok so
I think that the basic first question is
basically what what is a plaque in so
everybody talks about plugins and since
eclipse is out everybody say okay
everything is a plugin now and the world
consists out of plugins burn so let's
let's talk about let's make clear what
is a plugin maybe in contrast to add-ons
modules components and all those other
terms that are flying around so what do
you think what what is a plug-in well a
plug-in is an extension to an
application that is intended to be
extended so that was very generic
definition you have mentioned other
terms like modules and what
is probably the most generic term we
know in software and module is pretty
much everything that has some boundary
whereas if you look at components well
that is more specific components are
building blocks of some application but
typically components do not know which
application they are being made for and
that is the intent behind most
components and the intent of plugins is
different because they know exactly what
applications they are made for and vice
versa the applications really are
defined with with the idea of being
extensible so if you consider a web
browser and web browser is defined with
the idea of extending for our new data
formats and new presentation styles and
so on which is just not a component
style way of designing an application
mm-hmm
so you mentioned the web browser like
Firefox or whatever that could be
extended by plugins and if I think about
the the Eclipse idea of building the
whole application out of of different
platforms it seems like there there's a
difference between let's say maybe
plug-in based applications and should we
call it extensible applications well I'm
not sure we use the same wording here
talking about its lips I'd say well this
is basically a platform for plugins so
it provides plug-in mechanisms that's
the the core of the idea behind Eclipse
whereas if you look at at applications
one famous example is the Acrobat Reader
or the entire Acrobat program actually
the the idea of the Acrobat program was
not that it's a platform for some
extensible behavior but the idea was
that it's it's a document exchange
and the document display program and and
all the extensibility is like well we
can comment on it and so on are then
implemented in the style of plugins so
it's an inner style it's more like an
add-on the application is useful even
without plugins and this also is valid
for web browsers but with plugins or
add-ons you can increase the value for
the user okay so you say basically that
we have different kind of of let's say
plugin based systems so we have this
kind of applications that can be used
right away as they are and they the
functionality can be extended using some
some small plugins that sit on top of
those applications and that are maybe
other kinds of applications or you
mentioned the term platform or or let's
say maybe maybe it's an in plugin
infrastructure that allows you to build
applications out of plugins is that
correct yeah I'd say so
i-i've been using plugins with
industrial automation so to say so not
just the medical domain but also in
medical laboratories well we had
chemical analyzers and they needed a
particular communication protocol in
order to convey information about the
samples and the patients and so on and
we built a software that contacted many
different laboratory analyzers so it was
kind of an integration system and the
system actually would not have been
useful without any plugin for a chemical
analyzer so it's basically it's an
application that is intended to be
extensible by plugins and without the
first plugin it doesn't make any sense
at all but later on and this is the nice
thing about this kind of
application it can be extended well for
four years or decades even pretty much
like an operating system so when you
define an operating system you also have
entry points like device drivers and you
can pretty much add device drivers
anytime you like whereas an operating
system is very generic and so what I
used in the industrial environment is
the term driver actually to explain the
concept of a plug-in because when when
we did this in the in the early to mid
90s the term plug-in was not used very
often so it was a term that was used but
it needed explanation at that time
mm-hmm and nowadays everybody is talking
about plugins everybody's using plugins
and everybody has the idea that the
plug-in is something that can extend
behavior of an already existing system
and can may be closely integrated into
that system so that fits nicely into the
existing other plugins or other
applications yeah this is this is an
interesting point because what I've seen
is that we are talking about extension
points now and frameworks or
applications that make use of plugins
that typically offer a variety of
extension points that is a plug-in may
may come and bring very different things
not just a description or an
interpretation ability of some file
format but also some display properties
that it integrates into existing menus
of the application and so on so we have
a lot of areas where we can add behavior
to the application I think you mentioned
the term extension point I think we
should come back to that to that point
extension point in more detail later in
this episode because it sounds like
you're you're you're using the term
extension point is some some kind of
concept
on the conceptual level and I of course
think of extension point already in the
term of the Eclipse extension point
mechanism and stuff like that so we
should we should definitely discuss this
later on maybe so
but before we dive into the details of
how exactly a plugin can extend an
existing application using an extension
point technology or the concept of what
is an extension point or stuff like that
maybe we can we can elaborate a bit more
on what is a plug-in and what what makes
a plugin special so you said that
modules are very very generic or their
general concept and software engineering
and components are somehow different and
plugins or plugins are themselves
different from add-ons maybe maybe just
depending on what kind of application is
extended so and if I think about these
kind of modules I think the the module
has some kind of public visible behavior
and public visible API maybe and some
kind of private stuff I mean do we have
some similar concepts for for for
plugins maybe actually there are there
are different flavors of plugins so when
when I use plugins in the more technical
environment I use it two distinct
different applications basically so so
there is some application that is comes
from the hardware that adds some
measurements or measurements or therapy
or whatever and that goes right through
up to the user interface and the idea
behind this kind of plug-in is that the
plug-in provides the entire application
so nothing else needed but this plug-in
but the other ideas and that is
different in the Eclipse framework is
that plugins do not build upon one each
other in this domain
and this is to two very different
flavors of plugins those plugins that
build on top of the framework and other
plugins and those plugins that are
basically self-contained okay I see a
point a thing so you think that there
are plugins that are maybe built to be
used by other plugins or that extend the
functionality of the system but can
themselves be reused by other plugins so
they provide some kind of API for other
plugins and there's some kind of plugins
that are self-contained in the way that
they just add some functionality and
that's it yeah that's that's the key
point and if you look at what we we do
embedded software systems basically and
there it is important that some team who
has the the deep knowledge of for
example how to do a ventilation the the
knowledge about how best to present this
to the user is typically also contained
in this team or in that same part of the
organization so what what we do is we
split the teams and the the organization
into those application knowledge domains
and there we also have the architectural
concepts of saying okay we provide an
infrastructure where you can add all
your knowledge contribute all your
knowledge to the overall system that is
integrated later on and you can do it
without interference from any other team
whereas in the Eclipse framework the
idea is different people provide plugins
and other people say oh wow this is
great I can use it and they build more
plugins on top of these and in the end
you get a fine IDE environment
everything that you need with
kind of all the collective knowledge
that has been gathered over years which
is a different approach also widely
successful but the the underlying
technology is about the same that is you
have extensible applications mm-hmm okay
so maybe maybe let's go more and more
into details how those plaquing
techniques how they work so how do how
do these typical plaquing technologies
how do they work what what existing
technologies are there so I think we
have to mention somehow ours GI as one
kind of technical foundation for for
building plug-ins for for applications
may be there either self implemented
technique so what have you seen so far
for the technology the underlying
technology to me it is important that we
have an installation mechanism that the
the plug-in provider can use and that we
have a kind of well I'd say inversion of
control because that's a newly coined
term but it has been there all the time
that is whoever develops an application
prepares that plugins are installed at
startup time or at runtime and in it it
has a kind of registry where it looks
for what kind of plug ins are there and
then deploys them makes them run without
exactly knowing what exactly it is
because then that would be yeah
inverting the entire idea of a plug-in
because the application must not depend
on a particular plugin it may depend on
the fact that there are plugins but it
must not depend on a particular one okay
so what you're basically saying is if if
I understand that correctly is that you
somehow need a kind of of plugin info
structure that helps you to to discover
plugins which plugins are available
which plugins are installed and that
lets the application find those plugins
and at least use those plugins right
because they the application should not
know or the the basic infrastructure
should know which placards are exactly
installed but she'll be able to discover
them maybe it's startup time or at
runtime is that correct absolutely yeah
okay so and I think I was GIS is one of
those those infrastructures for for
plugin so helps you to to discover it in
this case for Java and to discover
plugins to to load and unload them
dynamically and this is exactly the
runtime that is used by the Eclipse
Eclipse platform Wow great really mob
proprietary platforms our applications
that that I've build and used we also
defined a lifecycle of plugins and then
then a very interesting point comes in
because what we see is that the
lifecycle of plugins really depends on
integrated plug-in portions so so
plug-in does not come just by itself but
there's a there's a whole package
included what do you mean by that if an
application kind of scans the registry
at startup it will find there is a
number of plugins installed but
depending on the purpose of the
application it does not necessarily
start all these at once but it may offer
some of these to the user and for this
you need things like a name and an icon
and maybe some some help text that
really come with a plug-in package but
this is not exactly the plug-in that is
does not fulfill a functionality yet so
this is more immersing some kind of
decorative metadata as you could you
could call it that way yes okay but it
may also include a nice photo
of some component that you want to
control using that plug-in so they could
be much involved in they're not
necessarily active software mm-hmm so in
the India's GI world this would be the
the manifest file where where the the
the name of the plug-in is there and and
some some some more information about
this plugin where this comes from and
what version of the plugin is meant by
by this deployable unit mm-hmm okay
sounds like this is the exact origin
okay I think M if we talk about this
this decorative metadata and that the
plugins have a life cycle
so they can I think for me a life cycle
means they can be installed and
uninstalled runtime and they can be
maybe updated at runtime that can be
started and stopped and stuff like that
and sound sounds similar to to your
experiences what I've seen is that there
are different state machines so
typically more than one the one that
controls the life cycle that you
describe is always included but for
those industrial systems embedded
systems that I've been working with we
also have another life cycle and that is
that of the communication state and both
live circuits interfere so you could say
the the communication state is a sub
state to the overall plug-in life cycle
so what do you exactly mean by a
communication state that sounds
interesting
well if you if you have a laboratory
environment and you have components that
come and go then your plugins need to
react somehow and depending on the
application you need to react
differently so if you have an
environment where you want to change
settings for some component that isn't
present at the very moment then this GUI
portion of the plug-in has a different
life cycle then that portion of the
plug-in that does the
on occasions via some Network protocol
okay and do you mean that or that does
this mean as well that if I write a
plug-in and I'm using maybe maybe maybe
some other plugins or some some
communication implementation stuff like
that um that um the basic plug-in
infrastructure should notify me somehow
if another plug-in comes in and then is
it get started and gets to get stopped
so that I can react to those other
plugins coming in coming in and going
away yeah there is always this moment to
some degree and again there are
differences so maybe we're focusing a
bit too much on this technical domain it
just happens to be the case that I'm
familiar with that and and what these
systems typically have is a detection
mechanism of what kind of pluggable
components that the user plucks and this
is typically external devices
what kind of components comes in and
leaves so there is always some some kind
of detection going on but this is a
different detection than what the
application does it start up because
there it scans the the registration for
what is the actual superset of plugins
and so to say of externally connected
components that I can deal with in total
and we have very little user interaction
on that level because that's basically a
topic of installation and the user does
not always install and the technical
domain but the user plucks together the
system and the software then reacts and
says ok well we have this plug-in life
cycle and the overall plug-in life cycle
has said yes I'm loaded I'm waiting for
something to happen and then we we come
to the communication life cycle meaning
now there is something present and now
we start to do the the communication the
presentation and the entire application
like the logic that is associated
the third project so okay Martin now now
I've told you a bit or maybe a bit more
about this this technical domain and I'd
like to hear how is it using Eclipse I
think using eclipse you have this this
the view of the world is that the world
consists out of plugins so everything is
built out of plugins so if you're very
very minimal plug-in infrastructure and
therefore they use their OSGi for as a
Java plug-in infrastructure that is I
think widely useful for maybe even
technical systems so it came out of the
embedded world and I think we we we have
a special episode on OSGi so listen to
that episode to get to get a more
detailed view on what is those GI
exactly yeah but some advertisement for
other F yourselves no well let's no but
I think in in Eclipse we have this the
view of the world is if plugins and
plugins provide functionality and
plugins can be extended by other plugins
so if is this idea of building plugins
on top of other plugins on top of other
plugins and for this let's say
extensibility you have basically two two
mechanisms so you can just use other
plugins I can say I would like to use
the functionality or the implementations
or the types of another plug-in this is
the direct use relationship or you can
inherit from types there or all those
those let's say basic object-oriented
mechanisms just by splitting up the
application into smaller or smaller
parts and you can define the the
dependencies between those parts and the
other mechanism is that you have or that
you make your your plugin extensible so
that is I think what you mentioned at
the beginning that you defined the
application to be extensible and to
just make sense if the application is
extended and and this is realized in the
eclipse world by the extension point
mechanism so you built a plugin and you
say okay this is my plugin and my plugin
should be extensible for example I am
the workbench and I have a menu called
refactor and this menu should be
extensible so I provide an extension
point I ask the implementation of the
workbench and the menu refactor for
example I say I am extensible and you
can extend that the menu and you have to
you can plug yourself into into my
workbench menu by giving me some
information some implementation and
those things and what what I what I
define what I tell the world is I am
extensible this is called the extension
point so I say I have an extension point
you can pluck yourself into my my
extension point you can extend my
implementation my plugin myself so other
plugins can can can come in and can
extend this menu item by providing an
extension this extension point so this
is I think similar to this kind of
inversion of control stuff where you do
not say ok my workbench and my menu
knows all the different menu items but
say ok I have a menu and you can extend
this menu by providing an implementation
of a menu item together with some
decorative metadata or stuff like that
and so another plugin can come in and
say okay I have an implementation I
would like to say I implement the
generic eye refactoring and I would
would like to plug this into this menu
and so I implement a plug-in and I say
ok I provide an extension to this
extension point so I plug my menu item
exactly into this menu
in the workbench refactor menu so this
is I think the basic idea of of
extension points in Eclipse and those
can be used all over the place and and
the basic idea is that the whole
application is built out of those
plugins and that I can say okay I would
like to to to add a menu item called
genera fie and I offer myself an
extension point to say okay III
implement this this menu action genera
five but there might be different
different algorithms to use to to genera
fie stuff in in java code and so i
provide an extension point for myself
say okay if other people find more
interesting ways to to to genera fide
java code they can plug their algorithm
implementations into my menu item genera
fie so my menu item itself is going to
be extensible and and so on so it's it's
recursively somehow so every plugin can
be extensible so and this I think allows
me to build really really interesting
architectures I think you you if you
started about thinking your application
in terms of plugins instead of thinking
about be extensible or be a huge
monolithic application or maybe maybe
even a componentized application then I
started to think of which parts of my
application are designed to be
extensible for the future and I think
this is this quite similar to what what
what you said before that in in in your
more technical domain you have these
applications and they those applications
they are built for extensibility and you
can implement for you mentioned
different algorithms and they can even
maybe maybe ten years later they can be
plugged into the system because the
system is designed to be extensible
and I think it fits nicely into this
view of building extensible applications
and an incremental incrementally grow
those applications so you can start
small design a very very small set a
very very small application split this
application to dip it into smaller parts
and say okay this application is
extensible and now maybe other team
members or the teams can extend this
application and add functionality and
they can use their our parts are
extensible as well
so those applications can can grow over
time and I think this is a very very
interesting characteristic or maybe an
interesting feature off of plugin based
applications they can be grown over time
and fits nice into this kind of agile
adding staff to an existing running
system and I think it helps you to to
think about your systems not not just a
technical a technical perspective on how
to how to modularize
or how to split up your system to
different parts it helps you think about
how to how to design your system I think
well what do you think right what you
described is a very fascinating thought
because the systems really grow over
time over generations maybe even and you
cannot really foresee in the in the very
start where we would end and this is
this is a very interesting thought
because you don't need a master plan in
the first place on the other hand when
when I talk about yeah life supporting
system
I say well we really need to know what's
going on in that system so I might be
more restrictive in that domain which is
I think a natural thing to do so when I
talk about extension points we pretty
much know in advance what will be
extended there and all the supper that
that goes to
a life supporting system will be
controlled by our internal mechanisms
and actually we build all these plugins
in within our company but the idea is
really not to not to restrict people in
in their ideas and their knowledge but
more to make sure that everything that
goes on in the system really fits
together well and so the concept is not
exactly as open as you described it for
the Eclipse platform so you have some
some kind of guidelines or some kind of
quality of service agreement or or
safety level or whatever some some kind
of contract between the extensible part
of the application and the extension to
the plugins yeah we have and it's fairly
detailed when we could do an entire
episode out of that but but to make it
very brief the the contract contains
entry points like I want to add to the
number of values that we can display I
want to add to the waveforms we can
display I want to add to the trending
behavior I want to add to the alarm
intelligence that we have in place I
want to add to whatever but but all
these points are known by the
application so we do not have plugins
that build on top of one each and one
another but we have applications that
define where our plugins could fit in
mm-hmm but but you cannot build build
plug-ins that that provide themselves
new entry points we could of course
that's that's not a technical problem
but but now we are coming to okay how
are the relations between those those
different teams that we have
mhm because plugins for me it's a
vehicle to separate teams so we really
have so to say a separation of concern
mhm but no longer on on a very technical
level because that is limiting if you
have separations of concerns and you say
well one is the network developer and
another one is the database developer
and the third one is the GUI developer
then we kind of have very little room
for for integrating the application
because then we have to merge all these
concerns all of a sudden so the the idea
is to split the teams in a different way
and that is per application or plugin so
to say so plugin is is a way to slice
applications differently and then we
know it from the layered architecture
the layered architecture slices in terms
of different technology when you use
various plugins really can slice and
cuts in the other dimension they slice
per application part of the application
and they cut through all the technical
domains and typically in in a system you
need to have both in some way or another
so you can build this kind of a matrix
technical versus application and you
need to fill all the fields within this
matrix but the interesting point is how
how do you organize who shall work
together and what is your main focus and
what I found is that the main focus on
the application really brings you
forward much quicker then when you have
house so to say in a database or network
team and they are really top-notch and
they are the fastest in the world but
nobody needs what they build and we only
find out later I think I think you
mentioned a gig quite interesting quite
interesting architecture
all characteristic of those plugin based
systems because if I think about plugin
based systems or more or less about
architectural styles or architectural
categorizations all I think about this
is kind of layering this kind of
persistence layer and logic layer and UI
layer and all those those different
layers and that the idea of plugins is
somehow orthogonal to those layers so in
in places from the right build we often
used those layers as ideas so we
separate persistence from logic from UI
and and maybe some some some more layers
and and orthogonal to this separation we
build plug-ins for different um let's
say functional parts or domain parts of
the system so we end up with having in
this this matrix the the boxes in this
matrix where somehow the plugins so we
have a plugin for let's say the the
persistence for a specific part of a
system we have a plugin for for a logic
of a specific part of the system and we
have different plugin for the
presentation of the system and so on so
what all these plugins only make sense
together right yeah definitely so they
they in this case of course the UI layer
plugin of part a of the system will use
the logic layer of part a of the system
and in this plugin and will use the the
plugin for the persistence for for part
a of the system yeah and so what what we
do is we package all these together and
say well this is what we call it one
plug-in or a plug-in package in the end
but this may be just a terminology but
the important thing is that that we also
scale the organization that way mm-hmm
but I think it's it's similar somewhat
similar to
in the eclipse world - the term feature
so they have a set of plugins basically
is a feature and you can install a
feature a feature consists of a set of
plugins so if I say I would like to add
accounting management to my to my
banking system I would add maybe mmm
some some some persistence plugins
some-some two main logic plugins some UI
presentation plugins and and this this
package that is this is cut on the on
the domain on the domain level is it's
called feature so this is similar to
what what you would you mentioned with
the plugin package yeah that's exactly
the same concept okay so it's a seems to
me like eclipse will they used maybe
different names and but it's it seems
like maybe all the same concepts right
yeah yeah and the same old stuff so to
say yeah we've been there in the late
90s and actually I'm frightened a pepper
patterns paper back then and patterns
always imply that it's no innovation by
just one company but that its concepts
well known in the industry already so
plugins are really not not particularly
new yeah we we can we can we can put put
a link to to to your paper into the show
notes oh sure yeah people can redo those
those patterns or any any other material
from from from the late 90s you said so
why not interesting stuff and just be
sure to also add more recent links to
what's going on in the Eclipse world
sure sure definitely yeah we will we
will we will do this what I think is
interesting about plugin systems as well
as um that they could help
to scale the system so if I think about
this this idea of of the Eclipse
platform so I have an IDE platform and I
have a Java IDE built on top of this
platform and this Java ID is a platform
itself for building more specific job
IDE stuff or for j2ee or stuff like that
and there are some some more advanced
IDE the WTP toolkit or whatever that I
build on top of this platform adding
more and more plugins and so my system
ends up maybe consisting out of
thousands maybe even thousands of
plugins could be hard to configure
actually yes it's it it's for me it's
always a challenge to configure my
Eclipse IDE the way that I like but um I
think what what banks the Eclipse
platform or the Eclipse plugin
infrastructure interesting is that even
if you have installed 5,000 or 10,000
plugins into your system it does not
slow down at startup time it does not
slow down at runtime
it just activates those plugins that are
actually used during my session so if I
start my mind and I say oh today I'm not
interesting in Egypt way at all
okay so by the way I've never been
interesting in Egypt at all but if I'm
not using the EJB features of my of my
wtp plugin installation um those classes
are never loaded into the system those
UI elements are never activated those
perspectives are never do never consume
any memory and stuff like that so cement
system can cans can stay pretty pretty
small the memory and can can can be
healthy somehow because those plugins
are not activated so it would be
different if all those 10,000 plugins
will be activated and and classes are
loaded and then caches are instantiated
and then filled with some some values or
whatever it startup time so maybe you
can
I would just need to start my IDE in the
morning to work in the afternoon and
that that's not the case and I think
it's it's a benefit you gain from from
the pluckin architecture in the
extension point mechanism that is built
into the Eclipse platform and just as
one example of of plugin infrastructure
so what you just show is that the user
may select a subset of functionality and
the the trade-off is that you have the
selected functionality quicker in place
for your convenience of usage but it
later on you can have all the
functionality you just have to wait then
I'll potentially have to wait then and
this resembles pretty much what what web
browsers do as well so the Flash plugin
is typically not loaded before it's
really mean it and then when it's needed
there's even a selection process like do
you want to start flash now yeah so
plugins really offer interesting
alternatives where the user may select
things or may choose not to use a
particular plug-in and I'm just thinking
about those thousands and and millions
of plugins and how they all interrelate
maybe it's it's worth mentioning that in
in those systems that that I've
architected are helped architecting that
we have actually different plugins
different plugins meaning well of course
all plugins are different but we have
from the application for seeing
different kinds of plugins so one those
that slice the application as I've
taught you but then we also have places
for plugins that integrate other plugins
as well but these are
explicitly called integration plugins
and with these plugins we have the
ability to also address or access other
plugins that are already there
so this is kind of the the the the
product creating plug-in there's
suddenly some place where we know
everything that's going on in the system
and where we can access private
information of plugins that the core of
the Cape application is not aware of and
this is really an important thing to add
value to the system because that's
that's where the interesting stuff is
going on okay so you think that you
typically in those applications you have
different plans it may be flavors or
different kinds of plugins yeah
different kinds of peers
yeah or types so to size it's actually
it on a very large scale it resembles a
type system but that's really a very
large scale okay maybe maybe two too
high level for our episode today right
maybe well what we what we are about but
a lot of things are about a software
engineering is raising the level of
structure here that we deal with and and
by this by this being more more powerful
yeah that's that's a famous proverb I
know it on the other hand we know that
our ability to envision applications
will always exceed our ability to
implement that it was Grady Booch who
said that we had interviewed great but I
don't know if he mentioned that in the
interview I don't think so but maybe we
can ask him so to to to wrap up somehow
this episode I think um maybe we can we
can collect some some ideas and then
some some let's say some some some some
guidelines or some guidance when should
I use plugins and why should I use
plugins so are the typical that's other
typical situations where you would say
in this situation I would use I would
introduce a plugin infrastructure and I
will split up the application into
different plugins and maybe some some
ideas well I'm inclined to use them all
over the place and I just wonder why
that is and I think one of the reasons
that we have not mentioned yet is that
they also help you to to focus to focus
on what is important about the
application you build and what is
optional mm-hmm and you can easily
factor out all those things that are
optional by saying I'll put them into a
plug-in sometime I think I observed a
pretty pretty similar stuff in in one of
my projects where we built a platform I
a plugin based platform for for
insurance applications and by adding
more and more applications on top of
this platform we observed it we have to
make more and more things of the
platform optional so we extracted them
out of platform and putting them and we
put them into separate plugins that can
be used or can be not used just
depending on the application you would
like to build on this platform so yeah I
think I absolutely prison a pretty
similar thing so when would you not use
plugins then well that's a that's a
tough question for me because I think I
think it's pretty similar the way the
way you think because I would like to
use OSGi and and plug and play stuff all
the time
I will never implement I would like to
never implement it
largest Java system without plugins but
if you ask me that way maybe I would
think if I if I will build very very
very small systems maybe just consisting
of a few classes maybe few small classes
so it maybe can you can even implement a
huge system out of five classes but and
those classes are pretty huge I've seen
systems like that so please do so I mean
same five classes and very very very
very few few methods and lexical
whatever so they're very small systems
I'm not sure if I would I would use the
the huge overhead I'm not the huge the
whole overhead of a plugin
infrastructure for that kind of systems
but typically those plugin
infrastructure SEC they're small they're
lightweight they're they're fast so in
the OCI example and is an example for
very small small plugin infrastructure
you can even use those plugin
infrastructure on a cell phone or on an
other embedded devices and maybe you
know the Java chip or whatever so so
it's it's even useful for those small
memory limited performance limited
environments so maybe it's a it's a
matter of the overhead involved to make
plug-in structural work compared to the
overall overhead of the project so if
it's more than a few percent it's
probably not worth it but do you think
it's it's it's a lot of overhead to to
introduce the plug-in infrastructure
it's it's a lot of overhead problem
depending on your project size but the
overhead is not to use the
infrastructure of plugins but to really
make up your mind of what shall be
extended
and what shall not be extensible and
what could be optional and so on so if
you have sufficiently small applications
you just are not concerned about all
this
I see so we haven't talked about about
this at all but I think it's an
interesting topic to think about we said
that the applications they need to be
designed to be extensible so does this
mean to do a lot of upfront design to
make those system extensible or maybe
not I know from the Eclipse team that
they build those kind of extension
points and those are those points that
makes an application extensible that
they build those extension points only
if they have a client that actually uses
this extension point right away so they
do not build those extension points up
front just by thinking of this could be
a very very very nice point to be
extensible they say okay we actually we
already have a client that asked for
this extensibility and then we provide
this extensibility and not upfront it
slightly different in the world where
where I work but not so much because the
domain knowledge is there and then do my
knowledge also says we're a product
needs to be extensible for a particular
application so it's it's well known but
then we do it by a big design up front
but this is this is not really something
that takes years because all the
developers familiar with the domain are
immediately familiar with the extension
points and why they are there but the
difference is is maybe in the evolution
of what's going on because what you
described works probably best if
somebody who says well this is a very
useful plugin and I would like to extend
it somehow can
either approach the the initial producer
of the plugin the developer or if he
could actually change the plugin because
it's open source because then the the
extension points that are missing can
easily be added and and this this will
make for very powerful architectures
actually okay I think there's a lot of
lot of more questions coming up right
now maybe because of what means
extensibility the evolution of those
platforms of api's and stuff like that
but maybe it's a bit a bit too much for
this episode we can we can discuss this
in a future episode maybe so it was a
long wrap-up and so would you like to to
to add something at the end some some
kind of some pearls of wisdom some
pearls of wisdom
[Laughter]
well don't be afraid if you cannot make
use of the Eclipse framework it's still
possible to do plugins and it's worth it
great so Klaus thank you very very much
for this for this episode and for being
being on the show and hope to hear you
soon again yeah that was great fun thank
you very much thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website and
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for se radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and slash dog
buttons to contact the team place an
email to team and SI radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie crowd and
the pot safe music network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle
[Music]